Preliminary Guide to The Black Box recorded poetry magazine, DC poets collection, 1973-1986 MS2172
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
The Black Box recorded poetry magazine, DC poets collection
1973-1986
1974-1985
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Watershed Foundation
MS2172
7 Linear Feet
The Black Box, the cassette-tape poetry magazine, undertook an ambitious documentary project in 1975 to record all the working poets in the Washington area. The editors estimated that this amounted to between two and three hundred poets. A representative spectrum was chosen for a special D.C. issue of Black Box and to air on several radio programs. The staff of the D.C. project included writers, editors, teachers of poetry and communtiy activists. The collection contains audiotapes, audiocassettes, and index cards for the Washington poets who were part of The Black Box cassette-tape poetry magazine. These tapes are recordings of local Washington D.C. poets for a special issue of the Black Box. Each recording includes an information sheet with technical data about the recording and a list of the poems read by the poets. The recordings date from 1973-1986 with the bulk falling between 1973-1986.
Arrangement Note
Organized into three series: audiotape poetry recordings, Black Box audiocassettes, and Index.
Historical note
The Black Box, the cassette-tape poetry magazine, undertook an ambitious documentary project in 1975 to record all the working poets in the Washington area. The editors estimated that this amounted to between two and three hundred poets. A representative spectrum was chosen for a special D.C. issue of Black Box and to air on several radio programs. The staff of the D.C. project included writers, editors, teachers of poetry and communtiy activists. The project was designed to be multi-racial and multi-cultural.
An issue of Black Box consisted of two 90-minute cassettes and included between 18 and 20 poets. Black Box was funded through a grant from the National Edowement for the Arts.
This special D.C. issue dated 1976 was the eighth issue of Black Box and was devoted exclusively to Washington, D.C. poetry. The editor, Alan Austin, remarked on the project that "an unusually large number of Washington poets --both black and white-- seem to be writing 'story' poems, narrative or dramatic poems which focus on character development; such poems are frequently concerned with encounters across barriers of class and race.... Another interesting discovery was that many of the poems we recorded were either influenced by or directly related to music."
Scope and Contents Note
The collection contains audiotapes, audiocassettes, and index cards for the Washington poets who participated in The Black Box cassette-tape poetry magazine. These tapes are recordings of local Washington D.C. poets for a special issue of the Black Box. Each audiotape includes an information sheet with technical data about the recording and a list of the poems read by the poets. The poets include among others E. Ethelbert Miller, Essex Hemphill, Grace Cavalieri, Chasen Gaver, Roland Flint, Lady Amir, and Adesanya Alekoye. There are also recordings of a poetry reading at the University of Maryland and a symposium in the District of Columbia. The recordings date from 1973-1986 with the bulk falling between 1973-1986.
Acquisition Note
Gift of the Watershed Foundation and the Poetry Committee of the Greater Washington Area, June 12, 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Related Materials
Five editions of Black Box were donated in 2021 by E. Ethelbert Miller within an addition to his collection (MS2215). They are found in Series 1, Subseries 3. The donated volumes are 2, 4, 6, 16, and 17. Volumes 2 (1972) and 4 (1974) predate the main documentary project which started in 1975.
Audiocassettes; Audiotapes; Gaver, Chasen; Cavalieri, Grace; Miller, E. Ethelbert
- audiotape poetry recordings, 1973-1984; 1973-1976; Series 1; 6 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains audiotapes recordings of Washington, D.C. Poets reading their work. There are also recordings of a Symposium in Washington D.C. related to poets, writers talking about upcoming legislation. Representatives from the National Endowment for the Arts attended and spoke. The symposium took place in 1984. Each recording includes an information sheet with technical data about the recording and a list of the poems read by the poets.
  Arrangement
  Arranged using the original audiotape number assigned by Black Box. This number is noted in a summary note for each recording.
  - Linda Goss, Clay Goss, Donna Mungen, Debbie Wood BB Studio Sessions, 1974 August 3; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    General
    original number of the tape: D-103A; 1/2 tk - 7 1/2 ips - tails out
  - Mae Miller Sullivan BB Studio, 1974 August 3; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 2)
    original number of the tape: D-103B; c. 25 min.
  - Tina Bradshaw, Ethelbert Miller, Adesanya Alakoye BB Studio sessions, 1974 August 3; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 3)
    original number of the tape: D-103C; 1/2 tk - 7 1/2 ips - tails out
  - Walt Christopher Stickney BB Studio, 1974 December 5; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 4)
    original number of the tape: D- 104; 1/2 tk -stereo - 7 1/2 ips
  - Jim Gardner BB Studio, 1975 January 5; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 5)
    original number of the tape: D- 105; 1/2 tk -stereo - 7 1/2 ips
  - Glen Stapler BB Studio DCPDP, 1975 March 15; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 6)
    original number of the tape: D- 106
  - Robt Newman, Karren Alenier BB Studio DCPDP, 1975 April 20; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 7)
    original number of the tape: D- 108
  - Tamu Moore, Donna Walters, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 8)
    original number of the tape: D- 113
  - Pat Garfinkel, Shirley Cochran BB Studio, 1975 July 16 - 1975 July 23; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 9)
    original number of the tape: D- 114; Pat Garfinkel was on July 16 and Shirley Cochran on July 23. 1/2 tk stereo 7 1/2 ips
  - Terence Winch BB Studio, 1975 June 27; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 10)
    original number of the tape: D- 115
  - Richard Harteis and Roger Greenwald, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 11)
    original number of the tape: D- 116
  - Tim Duglos, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 12)
    original number of the tape: D- 117
  - Tom Torosian BB Studio, 1975 July 30; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 13)
    original number of the tape: D- 118
  - Pat Marston BB Studio, 1975 July 30 - 1975 September 21; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 14)
    original number of the tape: D- 119 1st session July 30 and 2nd session September 21; 1/2 tk - stereo- 7 1/2 ips.
  - W. Dale Nelson BB Studio, 1975 August 3; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 15)
    original number of the tape: D- 120; 1/2 tk - St - 7 1/2 ips
  - David Allen BB Studio, 1975 August 3; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 16)
    original number of the tape: D- 121; 1/2 tk - St - 7 1/2 ips
  - David McAleavey BB Studio, 1975 August 6; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 17)
    original number of the tape: D- 122; 1/2 tk - St - 7 1/2 ips
  - Curtis Slaman BB Studio, 1975 August 6; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 18)
    original number of the tape: D- 123; 1/2 tk - St - 7 1/2 ips
  - Steve Cohen BB Studio, 1975 August 6; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 19)
    original number of the tape: D-124 1/2 tk - ST- 7 1/2 ips.
  - Mac Wellman BB Studio, 1975 August 11; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 20)
    original number of the tape: D-125 1/2 tk - ST- 7 1/2 ips.
  - Karl Freivalds, Fred Rachford BB Studio, 1975 August 13; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 21)
    original number of the tape: D-126 1/2 tk - ST- 7 1/2 ips.
  - Bob Nelson BB Studio, 1975 September 3; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 22)
    original number of the tape: D-127 1/2 tk - 7 1/2 ips.
  - Philip Periman BB Studio, 1975 September 14; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 23)
    original number of the tape: D-128 1/2 tk - 7 1/2 ips.
  - Columbia Station (live) Ned Bernton, Myra Sklarew, Roland Flint (R.I.), undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 24)
    original number of the tape: D-129 1/2 tk - Stereo - 7 1/2 ips.
  - Col. Sta. Roland Flint, Ira Bruckner, Pat (r.2), September 17; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 25)
    original number of the tape: D-130
  - David Washington, September 17; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 26)
    original number of the tape: D-131; Heads out - mono
  - Bob O'Meally, Lady Amir, Karen Morgan, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 27)
    original number of the tape: D-132
  - Lady Amir, Clinton Nelson, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Reel 28)
    original number of the tape: D-133
  - Robert Abney, Fred Strother Studio, 1975 September 15; Series 1 (Box 2, Reel 1)
    original number of the tape: D-134
  - Adesanya Alekoye BB Studio, 1974 Fall; Series 1 (Box 2, Reel 2)
    original number of the tape: D-135
  - Amma Khalil and E. Eth. Miller [E. Ethelbert Miller], undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Reel 3)
    original number of the tape: D-136
  - Otis Williams, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Reel 4)
    original number of the tape: D-137
  - Werner Low, 1975 September 22; Series 1 (Box 2, Reel 5)
    original number of the tape: D-138
  - Ascension VIII (reel two) Dahomey, Zehraa'u Mahdi, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Reel 6)
    original number of the tape: D-140 Ascension #8
  - Ascension VIII (reel three) Zehraa'u Mahdi (conc.), Karen Morgan, Debbie Wood, Brenda Wiliams, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Reel 7)
    original number of the tape: D-141 Ascension #8
  - Lorraine Hutchins Studio, 1975 September 28; Series 1 (Box 2, Reel 8)
    original number of the tape: D-142
  - Gabrielle Edgecombe, 1975 September 29; Series 1 (Box 2, Reel 9)
    original number of the tape: D-143
  - Pat Clary, Ned Bernton Studio, 1975 October 1; Series 1 (Box 2, Reel 10)
    original number of the tape: D-144
  - Univ. MD. open reading, 1975 April 24; Series 1 (Box 3, Reel 1)
    original number of the tape: D.C. - 101B; 1/4 tk mast (from CRO2 loc. tape) reel one of two
  - Univ. MD. open reading, 1975 April 24; Series 1 (Box 3, Reel 2)
    original number of the tape: D - 101; 1/4 tk mast (from CRO2 loc.) reel two of 2
  - Black Poetry, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Reel 3)
    original number of the tape: D - 102
  - Marathon reel one, 1975 April 1; Series 1 (Box 3, Reel 4)
    original number of the tape: D - 107
  - Marathon reel two, 1975 April 1; Series 1 (Box 3, Reel 5)
    original number of the tape: D - 107B
  - Marathon reel three, 1975 April 1; Series 1 (Box 4, Reel 1)
    original number of the tape: D - 107C
  - Patty Hardee, Tom Webner, Roger Greenwald, Peter Noterman, 1975 May 18; Series 1 (Box 4, Reel 2)
    original number of the tape: D - 109
  - DC Poets, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Reel 3)
    original number of the tape: D - 110; listed on the playlist are 1)unknown woman 2)Michael S. Weaver 3) Ethelbert [Miller] 4)Sharon Douglas 5)Linda Jenkins (w/flute)
  - Ira Bruckner, Walter Moore, JNO. McNally BB Studio, 1975 June 4; Series 1 (Box 4, Reel 4)
    original number of the tape: D-111
  - Jane Flanders, Hedy Reid, Ann Becker, 1975 June 13; Series 1 (Box 4, Reel 5)
    original number of the tape: D-112
  - Nancy Raine BB Studio, 1975 September 24; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 1)
    original number of the tape: D-145
  - W.A. Gardiner, Studio, 1975 October 6; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 2)
    original number of the tape: D-146
  - Beatrice Murphy and Molly Kruga, Studio, 1975 October 19; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 3)
    original number of the tape: D-147
  - Carl Bode, Studio, 1975 October 19; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 4)
    original number of the tape: D-148
  - Barbara Burman and Beth Burbank, Studio, 1975 October 12; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 5)
    original number of the tape: D-149
  - Nancy Prothro, Studio, 1975 October 13; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 6)
    original number of the tape: D-150
  - Tina Darraugh, Studio tape, 1975 October 15; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 7)
    original number of the tape: D-151
  - Sharon Mackin and Chasen Gaver, Studio tape, 1975 October 19; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 8)
    original number of the tape: D-152
  - Dave Kresh, Studio, 1975 October 19; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 9)
    original number of the tape: D-153; 1/2 tk - stereo - 7 1/2 ips
  - Leland Gamson and Ellen Carter, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 10)
    original number of the tape: D-154
  - Geoffrey Himes and Marty Brown, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 11)
    original number of the tape: D-155
  - Mary Brown and Jessie Harris, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 12)
    original number of the tape: D-156
  - Marlene Brim, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 13)
    original number of the tape: D-157
  - Rita Saseine and Ralph Robin, studio tape, 1975 October 27; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 14)
    original number of the tape: D-158
  - Ron Weber, studio tape, 1975 October 27; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 15)
    original number of the tape: D-159
  - Sauci Churchill and Robt Harding [Robert Harding], studio tape, 1975 October 29; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 16)
    original number of the tape: D-160
  - Claude Seymour and M.V. Capobianco, 1975 October 29; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 17)
    original number of the tape: D-161
  - Lisa Ritchie, Studio, 1975 October 29; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 18)
    original number of the tape: D-162
  - Ascension #9 reel 1, Michele Parkerson, Gerrard Brown, Patrice Wilson, 1975 October 28; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 19)
    original number of the tape: D-163; Howard Library
  - Ascension #9 reel 2, Otis Williams and Marlene Graham, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 20)
    original number of the tape: D-164
  - Ascension #9 reel 3, Connie Carter, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 21)
    original number of the tape: D-165
  - Ascension #9, Winston Napier and Essex Hemphill, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 22)
    original number of the tape: D-166
  - Ascension #10, Chas Jamison [Charles Jamison] and Kwaku Walker, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 23)
    original number of the tape: D-167
  - Ascension #10, Kwaku Walker (con't.) and Makeda and Gary Austin (Lorton wkshp. - 1 poem), undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 24)
    original number of the tape: D-168
  - Ascension #10, Ambrosia Shepard, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 25)
    original number of the tape: D-169
  - Ascension #10, Karl Carter, Robt. Boyd [Robert Boyd], Mike Burless, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 26)
    original number of the tape: D-170
  - Charles Winter, Studio, 1975 November 5; Series 1 (Box 5, Reel 27)
    original number of the tape: D-172
  - Rita Wilson, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 1)
    original number on tape: D-173
  - Ruth Rinker, studio, 1975 November 9; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 2)
    original number on tape: D-174; 1/2 tk - st.
  - Deirdra Baldwin, studio, 1975 November 3; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 3)
    original number on tape: D-175; 1/4 track
  - Richard DeCof, studio tape, 1975 November 3; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 4)
    original number on tape: D-176; 1/4 track tape
  - Robert Sargent, studio, 1975 November 3; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 5)
    original number on tape: D-177; 1/4 track
  - Lisa Schwebel, studio, 1975 November 9; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 6)
    original number on tape: D-178; 1/2 tk
  - Diane DeVaul, studio, 1975 November 9; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 7)
    original number on tape: D-179; 1/2 tk stereo
  - Rod Jellema, studio, 1975 November 12; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 8)
    original number on tape: D-180; 1/2 tk stereo
  - Deborah Sollers, BB studio, 1975 November 12; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 9)
    original number on tape: D-181; 1/2 tk - ST - 7 1/2 ips.
  - Beatrice Stenly, studio, 1975 November 17; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 10)
    original number on tape: D-182
  - James Lee and Tom Lyon studio, 1975 November 23; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 11)
    original number on tape: D-183; 1/2 tk - ST- 7 1/2
  - Jeremiah Lawson and John Pauker, studio, 1975 November 23; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 12)
    original number on tape: D-184; 1/2 tk - ST- 7 1/2 ips
  - Harvey Frye, studio tape, 1975 December 1; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 13)
    original number on tape: D-185
  - Hugh Walthall, studio, 1975 December 8; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 14)
    original number on tape: D-186
  - Laura Kennedy, studio tape, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 15)
    original number on tape: D-187; 7 1/2 ips
  - Wendy Stevens, studio, 1975 December 29; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 16)
    original number on tape: D-189; 7 1/2 ips
  - Greg Hannan, BB studio, 1976 January 7; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 17)
    original number on tape: D-190; 1/2 tk - ST - 7 1/2
  - Jim Beall and Catherine O'Neill, studio, 1976 January 14; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 18)
    original number on tape: D-191
  - Ann Darr, studio, 1976 January 18; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 19)
    original number on tape: D-192
  - Rick Cannon and Laurie Sphunt, studio, 1976 January 18; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 20)
    original number on tape: D-193
  - Terry Hegarty, 1976 January 26; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 21)
    original number on tape: D-194
  - Grace Cavalieri, studio, 1976 March 28; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 22)
    original number on tape: D-195; 1/2 tk - 7 1/2 ips
  - Jeff Miner and Mike Roth, studio session, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 23)
  - Robert Hinton, studio, 1976 March 29; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 24)
  - Tiemann songs reel 1 of 3, 1974 January 23; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 25)
    15 ips
  - District Symposium, 1984 April 9; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 26)
    reel 1 of 4
  - District Symposium, 1984 April 9; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 27)
    reel 2 of 4
  - District Symposium, 1984 April 9; Series 1 (Box 6, Reel 28)
    reel 3 of 4
  - District of Columbia Symposium, 1984 April 11; Series 1 (Box 7, Reel 1)
    Reel 4 of 4
  - Charles Ault, 1976 October 17; Series 1 (Box 7, Reel 2)
    Cleveland, Ohio by Barbara Pomeroy. 3 3/4 ips, side 1: 70 min. side 2: blank.
- Black Box audiocassettes, 1978-1986; Series 2; 0.75 Linear Feet
  This series contains audiocassettes of issues of The Black Box cassette-tape poetry magazine. The tapes date from 1978-1986.
  Arranged in the order of the Black Box recording number. This number is noted in a summary note for each recording.
  - An Ear to the Earth selected poems of Carolyn Kizer, 1977; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1, Cassette 1)
    tape number: C-103
  - A Whittemore Miscellany Reed Whittemore, 1978; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1, Cassette 2)
    tape number: C-116
  - Daddy original poems by Chasen Gaver, 1978; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2, Cassette 1)
    tape number: C-122
  - Say It by Roland Flint, 1979; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2, Cassette 2)
    tape number: C-123
  - Jazz in Praise of God by Owen Dodson, 1979; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 3, Cassette 1)
    tape number: C-131
  - Internal Foreigner by Peter Klappert, 1984; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 3, Cassette 2)
    tape number: C-162
  - Landscape with Tractor by Henry Taylor, 1985; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4, Cassette 1)
    tape number: C-185
  - In need of a mountain by Robert Vargas, 1986; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4, Cassette 2)
    tape number: C-197
  - Promising the Air Stanley Plumly, 1985; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1, Cassette 1)
    tape number: C-198
  - Stacy Tuthill notes from learning factory, undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1, Cassette 2)
  - Women writing 2, undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 2, Cassette 1)
  - Natives, Tourists and Other Mysteries Emerging Washington poets edited by Anne Becker, 1985; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 2, Cassette 2 - 3)
- Index, undated; Series 3; 0.25 Linear Feet
  This series contains an index of poets included in the Black Box cassette-tape poetry magazine. Often the index card will include a reference to the recording number in which the particular artist appeared. These cards are not dated.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Index: A, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Index: B, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Index: C, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Index: D, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Index: E, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Index: F, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Index: G, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Index: H, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Index: I, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Index: J, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Index: K, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Index: L, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Index: Mc, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Index: M, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Index: N, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Index: O, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Index: P, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Index: Q, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Index: R, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Index: S, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Index: T, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Index: W, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Index: XYZ, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 23)